Guide to the Kenneth Donaldson Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Kenneth Donaldson papers
1943-1982
MS 1677
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
5.5
The papers consist of correspondence, legal documents, hospital records, and publicity materials. They document Kenneth Donaldson's years as a patient at the Florida State Hospital, his efforts to obtain his release from the hospital, and the media coverage of him after his release and of his victory in the Supreme Court. Correspondence includes Donaldson's communication with friends, legal advisors, and medical staff.
Donaldson, Kenneth
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Beverly A. Reaves, 1995.
Arrangement
Arranged in four series: I. Correspondence, 1952-1975, II. Legal Documents, 1955-1978, III. Hospital Records, 1943-1972, IV. Publicity, 1971-1982.
Scope and Contents
The papers consist of correspondence, legal documents, hospital records, and publicity materials. They document Kenneth Donaldson's years as a patient at the Florida State Hospital, his efforts to obtain his release from the hospital, and the media coverage of him after his release and of his victory in the Supreme Court. Correspondence includes Donaldson's communication with friends, legal advisors, and medical staff.
The papers primarily document the life of Kenneth Donaldson during the years 1957 to 1971 when he was a patient at the Florida State Hospital. The papers provide insight to Donaldson's struggle to obtain his release from the hospital and a case study of the treatment of people suffering from, or perceived to be suffering from, mental illness during the 1950s and 1960s. Legal documents consist of petitions, depositions, transcripts, briefs, and opinions. Aside from a police identification card issued by the Miami Police Department in 1956, there are no original photographs of Donaldson in the papers.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
Kenneth Donaldson was born on May 22, 1908, in Erie, Pennsylvania. His birth name was William Kenneth Donaldson and he was the son of William and Marjorie Donaldson. He grew up in Erie, Cleveland, and Syracuse, New York, and attended Syracuse University for a year and a half. He married after he left school and he and his wife, Olive, had three children: David, Beverly, and Peter.
In 1943, after suffering a nervous breakdown, Donaldson was committed to the Marcy State Hospital in Marcy, New York, for four months. Donaldson felt he was the victim of slander and harassment, maintaining that people made derogatory comments about him behind his back, tampered with his mail, and put medication in his food. In an attempt to escape these perceived threats, he changed his name to Kenneth McCullough in 1953 and again in 1955 to Kenneth Donaldson. Now divorced, Donaldson moved from town to town and held several different jobs. In 1956, he was admitted to Philadelphia General Hospital and was treated for paranoid schizophrenia.
Upon his release from Philadelphia General Hospital in 1956, Donaldson went to visit his parents in Florida. In December 1956, his parents signed an inquisition of incompetency authorizing the police to arrest him. Donaldson was committed to the Florida State Hospital in Chattahoochee in January 1957 and was re-diagnosed as a paranoid schizophrenic. Soon after, he began his attempts to obtain his release from the hospital by filing a series of petitions in a Florida district court for a writ of habeas corpus, claiming illegal imprisonment. He met with little or no success for years until the New York Civil Liberties Union agreed to represent him in court and, upon the advice of legal counsel, he convinced a doctor not affiliated with the Florida State Hospital to come to Chattahoochee to examine him.
The Florida State Hospital discharged Donaldson in 1971, quite possibly as a hedge against pending legal action. His case against the hospital, Donaldson v. O'Connor, reached the Supreme Court in 1975. The Court decided in favor of Donaldson, ruling that the hospital violated his civil liberties by keeping him hospitalized without providing treatment. In addition, the Court's decision upheld a lower court's order that two doctors at the Florida State Hospital pay damages to Donaldson amounting to $20,000. Donaldson wrote of his experiences in Insanity Inside Out, published in 1976. He toured the United States during the late 1970s, championing the rights of patients in mental hospitals and promoting his book. Kenneth Donaldson died on January 5, 1995 in Sierra Vista, Arizona.
Human rights; Insanity (Law) -- United States; Mental illness; Psychiatric hospital care; Donaldson, Kenneth
- Correspondence, 1952-1975; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  The series is arranged chronologically and consists largely of letters sent and received during Donaldson's time at the Florida State Hospital. The correspondence documents the relationships between Donaldson and his family and his attempts to obtain his release from the hospital. Of particular value is Donaldson's correspondence with George Stallings, a Florida State Representative who took an interest in Donaldson's case, and with Morton Birnbaum and Bruce Ennis, the lawyers who worked on the case and presented it before the Supreme Court.
  Correspondence between Donaldson and his longtime friend, John Lembcke, has been separated from the rest of the correspondence. This correspondence is noteworthy because, as Lembcke was the one person Donaldson trusted through the years, it provides a more personal view of Donaldson during his time at the Florida State Hospital. Because Lembcke dealt with Donaldson's financial affairs, the section also includes a small number of financial documents consisting of a bank book, dividend statements, and deposit slips.
  - General
    - 1952-1964 June (Box 1, Folder 1-16)
    - 1964 July-1966 May (Box 2, Folder 17-30)
    - 1966 June-1970 May (Box 3, Folder 31-46)
    - 1970 June-1973 December (Box 4, Folder 47-55)
  - Lembcke, John, 1964-1975, undated (Box 4, Folder 56-62)
- Legal Documents, 1955-1978; Series II
  Legal documents are arranged by court proceeding beginning with Donaldson's petitions for a writ of habeas corpus and culminating in Supreme Court opinions regarding his case. For each court case there may be court petitions, depositions, transcripts, briefs, and opinions. The series also includes a police identification card and name change affidavits.
  - Gadsden County (Florida) Court, 1963-1969 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Florida Appellate Courts, 1963, 1969 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Supreme Court of Florida, 1960-1969 (Box 5, Folder 3-6)
  - U.S. District Court
    - Petitions, 1965-1972 (Box 5, Folder 7-15)
    - Petitions, 1973-1978 (Box 6, Folder 16-17)
    - Discovery, 1971-1976 (Box 6, Folder 18-21)
    - Depositions, 1971-1976 (Box 6, Folder 22-28)
    - Trial transcripts, 1972 (Box 7, Folder 29-44)
  - U.S. District Court of Appeals, 1965-1973 June (Box 7, Folder 45-46)
  - U.S. District Court of Appeals, 1973 June-1975 (Box 8, Folder 47-48)
  - U.S. Supreme Court
    - Petitions, 1960-1970 (Box 8, Folder 49-52)
    - Briefs, 1970-1975 (Box 8, Folder 53-57)
    - Amicus curiae briefs, 1970 (Box 8, Folder 58)
    - Amicus curiae briefs, 1974 (Box 9, Folder 59-60)
    - Opinion, 1975 (Box 9, Folder 61)
  - Legal research, 1960-1975, undated (Box 9, Folder 62-68)
  - Amicus curiae briefs [related cases], 1973 (Box 9, Folder 69-71)
  - Miscellaneous legal documents, 1955-1963 (Box 9, Folder 72)
- Hospital Records, 1943-1972; Series III
  Hospital records are organized in rough chronological order according to a numbering system devised by Donaldson. The numbers appear in the upper right hand corner of the documents. The series begins with documentation from Marcy State Hospital and Philadelphia General Hospital. The bulk of the series is comprised of records from the Florida State Hospital. Donaldson's medical record and the correspondence between the doctors and his family are particularly revealing because they document the doctors' evaluation of him. Additional correspondence regarding Donaldson's hospitalization can be found in Series I.
  - Marcy State Hospital, 1943, 1954-1957, 1972 (Box 10, Folder 1)
  - Philadelphia General Hospital, 1956, 1966-1972 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Florida State Hospital
    - Donaldson medical record, 1956-1971 (Box 10, Folder 3-4)
    - General, 1956-1971 (Box 10, Folder 5-17)
    - General, 1956-1971 (Box 11, Folder 18-25)
    - Reports, 1954, 1970 (Box 11, Folder 26)
- Publicity, 1971-1982; Series IV
  Arranged by format and in rough chronological order, the series includes newspaper clippings, magazine articles, book reviews, conference programs, public appearance announcements, awards, and a copy of his book. Publicity chronicles Donaldson's time as a celebrity, after the Supreme Court decision when he conducted a book tour. Georgetown University included his case in a conference called Basic Issues of the Therapeutic State. The Yale University Law School studied the possible effects of the Supreme Court decision on the Connecticut Valley Hospital.
  - Articles, 1974-1980 (Box 12, Folder 1-7)
  - Awards/honors, 1977 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Clippings, 1971-1982 (Box 12, Folder 9-18)
  - Clippings, 1971-1982 (Box 13, Folder 19-33)
  - Conferences
    - Georgetown University conference, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 34-35)
    - Yale University project, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 36)
  - Insanity Inside Out, 1976 (Box 14, Folder 37)
  - Printed material, 1976-1977 (Box 14, Folder 38)
  - Public appearances, 1973-1980 (Box 14, Folder 39-41)